All right, let's get started. So, the
thing that we want to do um is we want
to write two functions. And
I'm just going to zoom my code out a
little bit. Okay, so this toggle die
hold function is one of the functions
we'll need to write. And this roll dice
function is the other function we'll
need to write. As always, I am going to
put my name and a description at the
top.
And then now we can get started. So if
we look over here, this toggle die hold
is receiving a number and that number
corresponds with this ID. And you can
see that on each of those lines. So I
need to write toggle die hold such that
it takes one of those numbers. So I'm
going to write function
toggle by hold and I'm going to accept
an ID and I'm going to adjust based on
what that ID says to do. So if we come
back over to the instructions, it says
we should accept a parameter called ID.
We've done that. Now we need to access
the corresponding image element for the
die and toggle the attribute data
active. So the attribute data active is
either storing true or false. And if we
and it says here that it starts as true
and we can actually confirm that. So
data active starts as true. So all of
those are true. So what we want to do is
we want to access the element based on
the ID. To do that we're going to say
document.getelement by ID. We're going
to pass in the ID that we received. And
then we're going to get attribute not
animations get attribute.
And the attribute we want is data
active.
And then um once we've got that, we want
to store it in a variable. Um I am going
to put a semicolon at the end of that
line. All right. So let's create a
variable called let current active
status equal grabbing that attribute.
Once we've got that attribute, we want
to toggle it. So we'll say um
let new status equal the current active
status. And if the current active status
is
um
if the current active status is true
then we want to set it to false.
Otherwise sorry yeah otherwise we want
to set it to true.
So basically we're saying if it is true
set it false. If it's false set it to
true.
And we do need to actually reapply that.
So we're going to say
document.getelement
by ID. We're going to access the ID.
We're going to call set attribute. The
attribute we want to set is data active.
And what do we want to set it to? We
want to set it to the new status.
Great.
Okay,
let's just go test this to make sure it
works. So, we're going to come to our
die roller. I'm going to inspect the
page. I'm going to rightclick here and
click inspect so that it pops open my
image. All right. So it has a data
active to equal to true if I click it.
Oh, I had a debug point. Um,
so it has data active equal to true. If
I click it, nothing happened. Let's
check the console. Um,
okay. So let's check our logic. Um, if
something doesn't work the way we
expect, we will want to put a
breakpoint. So I'm going to come to
sources. Going to click on script.js.
I'm going to put a break point here and
I'm going to click the die. Okay. So,
our current active status, it's going to
get that attribute. If we hit next, our
current active status is true. Um, true
should be slightly equal to true, not
equal on types, but it has single it has
quotes around it. So, if we make this
comparison, they should be equal. So,
the result of new status should be
false. We'll hit next. And the result of
new status is true.
H
current active status is true and we
made
H
well we know that the true comes back in
quotes. So let's just go adjust our
logic there. Um so we're going to say if
current status is exactly equal to the
text true then we want to set it to
false. Otherwise, we want to set it to
true. Um, we're going to remove our
breakpoint,
hit continue, reload the page, come to
elements, click the die, and now it's
adjusting. It's going from true to false
and false to true. So now our logic
works.
Um, let's look at the next step. The
next step is to either add or remove the
held class from the class list. The
class should be held if data active is
false. The class should not be held if
data active is true.
So, um, I'm just going to copy this so I
don't have to toggle back and forth
and I'm going to put it in here.
Okay.
So um new status is going to be either
true or false. Um and the new status is
going to be what the element currently
has as its status. So we can use new
status in this if statement. So we'll
say if and it says if
the class should be held if data active
is false. So if
data if new status so we'll say if new
status because we're checking if it's
true. If it's true the clash should not
be held. Well one of the ways you can
edit classes is you can say
document.getelement
by ID. Once you've got the ID then you
can access the class list. What that
does is it takes all of the CSS classes
that are listed out here and it converts
it into a list that you can add and
remove from. Because this is a
customuilt list, you have to use their
built-in methods. One of those built-in
methods is add and one of the built-in
methods is remove. So you can add and
remove classes. So if
the class is true, it should not contain
the held class. So we're going to remove
the held class. Otherwise,
we're going to add the held class.
Let's go see if that worked.
And it did. We can see that the class is
expanding to have held and then it's
being removed when we click off of the
die.
So, that correctly works. We can now
toggle the class. And I should probably
have some comments in here. So I'm going
to say grab the data active attribute
and toggle it.
And that will do all of that. And then
here we'll say apply the held class
accordingly.
Cool. So we've done part of it. Now we
can
um toggle these die. Um but what we want
is we want to roll all of the ones that
are still active.
And if we look at the instructions, it
says generate a random number for each
die that has the data active equal to
true. Um update the source and alt
attributes of the image accordingly. So,
if we look um the alt says die and then
um the number presently showing and
that's so that a screen reader can tell
someone what face is currently showing
on the die. So, um what we're going to
do is we're going to need to write this
roll the dice function.
So we'll say function roll the dice
and we need to access all of them that
have data active equal to true.
Well, one of the easy ways to do this is
to use query selector all.
And we can pass in a CSS selector. And
I'm going to select based on attribute.
And I'm going to select where data
active is
true
because I want all of the ones where
it's true. And I'm going to put single
quotes so that I can have the double
quotes inside of the selector. Okay. So
that should get me a list of all active
die. So, I'm going to say let all active
die or dice equal
all of those elements. So, it should
come out and it should grab each of
these image tags
um except for the ones that are false.
Then what I want to do is if we come
look at the instructions, I need to
generate a random number and update the
source and alt attributes of the image
accordingly. So I'm going to say for let
die of all active dice
and then I'm going to say let num equal
um math dolore
math do random and I'm going to multiply
it by six because this will give me a
number between 0 and five and if I add
one that'll give me a number between
zero and six. Then I want to take the
die and I want to set attribute. What
attribute do I want to set? Well, I want
to set its source. And what do I want to
set it source equal to? Well, right now
the source is images.png.
And that shows the one die face. So if I
want to follow that same pattern, then
the die face I want to show is images
slash whatever number I rolled.png.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
make a template string here and I'm
going to say images slash and then I'm
going to put in num and then I'm going
to put png. So, that will update um its
source attribute.
And if we look at its alt attribute, its
alt attribute I'm actually just going to
copy one of these. It says die and then
the number that was rolled. So, we're
going to say die set attribute alt
And we want to set it equal to and
instead of saying
die one,
we're going to say die
and then the number we rolled.
Okay,
that should roll the dice all except for
the ones that are not active. So, let's
just come over and test that. So, if I
click I'm gonna hold this one and I'm
click roll the dieice. And it says roll
dice is not defined. And
it's because this function that it calls
on the on click is called roll dice. And
I named mine the wrong wrong thing. I
called it roll the dice. So, I'm going
to update my function name. Come back.
Hold this first one. Click roll the
dice. All of the others changed. Roll
the dice. And I'm going to pin that one.
and pin that one. Pin that one. And now
I've got all the dice that match. Um,
and so let's just double check our
instructions. Um, we generated a random
number. We updated source and alt. Let's
just make sure source and alt are
correct. Uh, this is die one. This is
die object HTML element.
Okay. So, we updated the alt
incorrectly. So, we're going to come
here. Ah, I put die and I should have
put no because die is an HTML element
because this query selector grabs HTML
elements, stores them in all active
dice. Die gets pulled out of all active
dice which means die is an HTML element
and I put the wrong one here. So, we'll
save that. We'll reload this page. I'll
click that. I'll click roll the die and
it updated them. So, this one says alt
die one and has the correct image
showing. So, we've now correctly updated
source and image. Um, everything is
working as expected. So, we just need to
add some comments. So, I'm going to say
grab all active dice and
up
roll the dice and update source and alt.
And if we save that, we are